<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Tecnoprom Core</title><link href="http://javcasas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://javcasas.github.io/feeds/learning-how-to-learn.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://javcasas.github.io/</id><updated>2015-01-27T19:10:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Learning How to Learn</title><link href="http://javcasas.github.io/posts/2015/Jan/27/how_to_learn/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-27T19:10:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Javier Casas</name></author><id>tag:javcasas.github.io,2015-01-27:posts/2015/Jan/27/how_to_learn/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="the-art-of-improving-oneself"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Art of Improving Oneself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="introduction"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are born, and before we know what's going on, we are thrown into a school,
to update our knowledge of the world. At least us, the lucky ones, are thrown
into a school. Remember not everyone is as lucky as you, and may have to work
hard before he has the chance to learn to read and write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is: learning converts weak children into (mostly) decent and competent
adults. Learning and improving is what differentiates the human from the
animal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-zen-of-improving-yourself"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The zen of improving yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kung-fu masters spend decades practicing, punching and kicking, and that's how
they become masters. But I'm a bad and impatient young grasshopper. I'm not
willing to wait 50 years to become a master. I want to believe there is a way
to accelerate it, to accelerate the acquisition of knowledge, skills and
wisdom. And I think I have a point: some masters are incredibly young. So there
must be some difference between the way the young master learns, and the way
the old master learns. Otherwise young masters would not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="motivation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me, me, me. It's always me. I want to improve. I want to be better. I want to
be great, and awesome, and powerfull, and all that stuff. And I happen to be
a software developer, which puts me in a high learning career. Either learn and
improve, or become an obsolete old fart. So following from it, I want to
improve my way of improving, so I can be all that awesome in less time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-way-of-the-learner"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The way of the learner&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I used to learn the way I learn. Not really efective way. You know, you
spend all these years at school learning Maths, and Geography, and History, and
Language. But no teacher spends a friggin' minute teaching you how to learn. So
you discover your own way, which mostly works for school, but it's probably
sub-optimal, if not completely misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decades later, I read about the most popular MOOCs of 2014. And one of them was
&amp;quot;Learning How to Learn&amp;quot;. And it was an eye-opener for me. On this document, you
will find a reduced version of what's available on the MOOC, so you can have it
as a quick list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="focused-and-diffuse-modes-of-thinking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Focused and diffuse modes of thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your brain works in misterious ways, but the scientists have managed to
separate them into two main ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The diffuse mode: on this mode, your brain doesn't concentrate on anything
special. You think about everything at the same time: the groceries list,
today's bad traffic on the highway, the conversations you overheard at the
office today... Just a bit of everything. On this mode, your thoughs jump
around without focusing on anything. It's also the same mode you are on when
you are going to sleep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The focused mode: This is the mode you enter when you are concentrating in
order to solve a problem. All you can see is the problem in front of you. The
sexiest girl in the world could be dancing naked in front of you, and you
wouldn't see her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the focused mode is what you use to learn and to fix hard
problems. It's the sharp point of the though. But it's so concentrated, it
can't see any other solutions. On the other hand, the diffuse mode can see lots
of solutions, different approaches, and is the way to think &amp;quot;out of the box&amp;quot;.
But it's pointless, and hardly could fix anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And your brain can only be at one mode. So you have to learn how to juggle the
modes. How to go into focused, and diffused, on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="key-learning-techniques"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key learning techniques&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You open a text book. It's full of words. Definitely, not all the words are
important. Some of them are more important than others. And there is this
thing, called the &amp;quot;main idea&amp;quot;, which is what you should remember. And that's
probably the biggest point: remember the main idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember: You are not learning if you are not remembering. Techniques such as
highlighting fail often because the student concentrates into highlighting.
What matters at the end is what you remember. So the first technique of the
great learner, is to remember as much as possible of what has been studied.
Study a bit, close the book, try to remember as much as possible. The very
act of trying to remember helps push the knowledge into your long-term
memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main idea: Everything revolves around the main idea. You can't learn
properly until you have found the main idea and distilled it to it's minimum
components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After each lesson, you have 1 minute to write down the key ideas in their minimum components,
because you have just 1 minute. This will help memorize the core ideas and discard
the chaff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't learn. Do. You will never become a master until you do whatever you want
to learn. Read the text book, then apply what's written on the text book to
actually fix something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning takes time. In order to learn something, you have to repeat it several
times, over a long period of time. If you learn something in a day, it will be
forgotten in another day. The only way to make it stick is by repeating it over
several days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relax. Not everything can fit in your head in a day. Even worse, when your head
is stuck with the wrong answer, hammering it will only make it worse. Let your
mind wander away for a while, and let go the broken answer in order to make space
for the right one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interleave learning. Study several disciplines every day at different times. Your
brain works and improves when you make it switch between different tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise is awesome. Your brain relaxes when you exercise, your blood flows better,
the toxins go away, the belly fat dissolves, and you feel better. There is no bad side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep is very important. Your brain cleans up itself and reinforces ideas while
sleeping. So sleeping too little in order to study more is actually a bad idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="closing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastering learning is really worthy, specially in this day and specially for technical
and information professionals. Not a single day goes on where something new is discovered,
or a new technique is developed. So if you want to stay on top of everything, you certainly
need to be really good at learning and improving. So keep learning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="learn"></category><category term="learning"></category><category term="mooc"></category></entry></feed>